<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-24T13:23:43+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">A few words about the 48-team World Cup</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/world-cup-48-teams/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A few words about the 48-team World Cup"/><published>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/world-cup-48-teams</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/world-cup-48-teams/"><![CDATA[<p>From 2026 on, the Men’s Football World Cup will be played by 48 national teams, instead of the usual 32. The teams will be <a href="https://inside.fifa.com/about-fifa/organisation/fifa-council/media-releases/fifa-council-approves-international-match-calendars">divided into 12 groups of 4</a>, playing a single round-robin tournament, from which the top two and eight best third-placed will classify for the playoffs.</p> <p>It is not unreasonable to assume that FIFA’s main motivations behind the inclusion of 16 new countries are money (higher TV &amp; advertisement, and game-day revenues) and power (more political support from the confederations benefitted by the expansion), and those arguments <a href="https://www.uol.com.br/esporte/futebol/colunas/juca-kfouri/2023/10/04/a-copa-do-mundo-em-seis-paises.htm">find echo on a relevant part of the sports media</a>.</p> <p>Although I understand and agree with this view, I must confess that I think that the consequences of the expansion will be fantastic. First, <a href="https://www.bbc.com/sport/football/39448474">Africa is receiving 4 new spots</a>, while Asia is getting 3. Given the low representation of those continents in past editions of the competition, and also considering their recent strong performances, those places are definitely well-deserved. Additionally, Europe is taking 3 new places, which decreases the chances that football powerhouses such as Italy or the Netherlands will stay out of the tournament as it happened before. Finally, South America and its highly-competitive qualifiers receive one extra spot. This means that we are guaranteed to have several additional nations for which football is a central cultural aspect playing in the World Cup.</p> <p>Many journalists have <a href="https://blogdojuliogomes.blogosfera.uol.com.br/2017/01/11/duas-razoes-para-nao-gostar-da-copa-do-mundo-com-48-selecoes/">pointed out that the extra teams could decrease the technical level of the competition or even diminish the competitiveness of the regional qualifiers</a>. This is completely true. However, do we really care about the technical level in a World Cup? Do we really care about the qualifiers in general? I would safely assume that both answers are negative for most of the football supporters. For the first question, I would argue that the appeal of a World Cup is primarily driven by emotion rather than skill, especially at a time when European club football already provides weekly exhibitions of refined technique. As for the second question, it’s worth noting that the qualifiers already face a general lack of interest (at least in Brazil), with the exception of a few notable matches (e.g. against Argentina).</p> <p>Enough of my personal opinion. Let’s take one step back, and discuss the format of a World Cup with 48 teams. Before settling for the 12 groups with 4 teams scenario, FIFA had initially proposed 16 groups with 3 teams, with the top two classifying for playoffs. At that time, <a href="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f1af76ed86d6771ad48324b/606e51a178c5517440a676f1_JulienGuyon-FIFACollusion-RPpaper.pdf">this article written by the French mathematician Julien Guyon</a> gained prominence. In this paper, Guyon discusses the risk of collusion (i.e. the teams playing the last game of the group potentially match fixing so both advance) in groups of 3 teams and shows that the probability of collusion in at least one group is actually very high. The author also suggests alternative formats that could reduce the risk of collusion, and, interestingly, FIFA has adopted one of them. I am not aware of the impact of this particular paper (or the related literature) on the organization’s final decision, but it is always interesting to see how scientific reasoning can sometimes helps us to make robustly improved decisions.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[football world cup]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How do Brazilian engineering schools’ budgets compare globally?</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/engineering-budget/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How do Brazilian engineering schools’ budgets compare globally?"/><published>2024-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/engineering-budget</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/engineering-budget/"><![CDATA[<p>Some weeks ago, I attended the <a href="https://www.tudelft.nl/en/2024/me/news/tu-delft-mechanical-engineering-opens-new-robotics-lab">opening of one of TU Delft’s robotics labs</a> and was impressed by its infrastructure. This experience prompted me to consider whether such an investment would be feasible for a Brazilian engineering school. Not having the time for a proper analysis, I choose to present some relevant data that I quickly gathered comparing the budgets of one of Brazil’s leading engineering schools with those of some of its international peers.</p> <p>According to the University of São Paulo’s <a href="https://sites.usp.br/codage/gestao-orcamentaria/prestacao-de-contas/">budget plan</a>, the Polytechnic School (its engineering unit) is expected to have approximately R$ 375 million (or EUR 67 million) to spend in 2024. With around <a href="https://www.poli.usp.br/institucional/poli-em-numeros">8,500 FTE (Full-Time Employees)</a> (including undergraduate and graduate students, faculty, and administrative staff), the annual budget per FTE comes to about EUR 7,900.</p> <p>In contrast, TU Delft (Netherlands) had <a href="https://filelist.tudelft.nl/TUDelft/Over_TU_Delft/Feiten_Cijfers/jaarverslagen/TU%20Delft%20Jaarverslag%202022%20EN%20%28def%29.pdf">funding of around EUR 880 million</a> for 30,000 FTE in 2022, resulting in a ratio of EUR 29,000 per FTE, more than three times higher than the Brazilian school. At École Polytechnique (France), <a href="https://www.ccomptes.fr/system/files/2020-02/20200225-12-TomeI-ecole-polytechnique.pdf">a public report</a> indicates that the annual formation cost per student was about EUR 36,000 in 2016-17 (though this figure is not directly comparable to the other schools, it provides a rough estimate). Lastly, Polytechnique Montreal (Canada) <a href="https://www.polymtl.ca/renseignements-generaux/en/about-polytechnique">operates with a budget of EUR 150 million</a> for 10,000 FTE (2018-19), leading to EUR 15,000 per FTE, or twice the ratio of the Brazilian school.</p> <p>I point the interested reader to these schools’ annual reports to understand the specific details (sources, destinations, distribution of FTE, profile of the research programs, etc) of each budget. Needless to say, any errors in the data presented above are my responsibility, and these figures represent my best interpretation of the annual reports.</p> <p>Despite the limited depth of this analysis, the significant difference in budget per capita (2-3x) when comparing one of Brazil’s leading engineering schools with other top-tier international schools suggests that Brazilian engineering may lack the resources needed to compete globally.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[engineering]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The big casino of sports betting</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/sports-betting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The big casino of sports betting"/><published>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/sports-betting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/sports-betting/"><![CDATA[<p>As casas de aposta esportiva <a href="https://www.uol.com.br/esporte/futebol/ultimas-noticias/2023/03/31/patrocinios-de-sites-de-apostas-a-clubes-da-serie-a-batem-r-330-mi-por-ano.htm">dominaram o futebol brasileiro</a> nos últimos anos. Suas marcas parecem onipresentes: publicidade em TV e internet, patrocínios estampados em uniformes, outdoors. Curiosamente, até há pouquíssimo tempo, estas empresas ainda gozavam de lacunas tributária e regulatória que criavam incentivos adicionais à proliferação da atividade - situação que deve ser resolvida com uma <a href="https://g1.globo.com/politica/noticia/2023/07/25/mp-das-apostas.ghtml">recente MP proposta por Haddad</a>.</p> <p>Mas o que está por trás do interesse de tantos agentes em mediar apostas esportivas? Quais são os fundamentos da lucratividade dessa atividade? Apesar de nunca ter apostado em resultados esportivos (com exceção de uma pizza que tive de pagar para meu grande amigo Artur S. após a vitória da Itália na Eurocopa de 2020), pretendo apresentar algumas reflexões sobre a matemática das apostas.</p> <p>1) <strong>Funcionamento das apostas no Brasil</strong></p> <p>Para apostas no vencedor da partida, a casa precifica cotações para a vitória do mandante, visitante e empate. Por exemplo, suponha que a cotação do empate seja \(2.5\). Caso o jogo termine em igualdade de placar, para cada <code>$</code> 1 colocado nesse resultado, o apostador receberá <code>$</code> 2.50 (tendo, assim, uma rentabilidade de <code>$</code> 1.50 - pois o real inicialmente apostado faz parte do pagamento).</p> <p>2) <strong>Por que \(\frac{1}{\text{cotação}}\) pode traduzir a probabilidade do evento?</strong></p> <p>No nosso exemplo anterior, muitos sites indicarão que a probabilidade de empate implícita na cotação de 2.5 é \(\frac{1}{2.5} = 40\)%. Mas como justificar essa conta?</p> <p>Isso deriva de um argumento de <em>competição perfeita</em>. Em um mercado perfeitamente competitivo entre as casas de aposta, as cotações devem ser tais que o rendimento esperado para o apostador seja nulo (se as cotações apresentadas implicassem redimentos esperados positivos, a casa perderia dinheiro no longo prazo; se negativos, abririam oportunidade para que outras casas oferecessem melhores cotações e absorvessem <em>market share</em>).</p> <p>Sejam \(R\) a variável aleatória que representa o <strong>rendimento</strong> do apostador para cada <code>$</code>1 apostado e $k_{\text{evento}}$ a cotação de um determinado evento (e.g. vitória do mandante).</p> \[R = \begin{cases} k_{\text{evento}}-1 &amp; \text{se evento ocorre } (p_{\text{evento}}) \\ -1 &amp; \text{se evento não ocorre } (1-p_{\text{evento}}) \end{cases}\] <p>Então,</p> \[\mathbb{E}(R) = (k_{\text{evento}}-1)p_{\text{evento}} + (-1)(1-p_{\text{evento}}) = 0 \implies p_{\text{evento}} = \frac{1}{k_{\text{evento}}}\] <p>Ou seja, se a casa acredita que a probabilidade do evento é de \(50\)%, então, sob hipótese de competição perfeita, ela seria “forçada” (pela própria dinâmica do mercado) a oferecer uma cotação de \(k_{\text{evento}} = \frac{1}{p_{\text{evento}}} = \frac{1}{0.5} = 2\). É evidente que esta é uma explicação simplificada, mas ajuda a entender o racional. Argumentos similares (e com maior grau de formalidade) podem ser encontrados em livros básicos de Microeconomia.</p> <p>3) <strong>A hipótese de competição perfeita é válida na prática?</strong></p> <p>Não. Não há competição perfeita nesse mercado (que parece mais uma espécie de oligopólio) e, ainda, há custos de operação que devem ser cobertos pela casa.</p> <p>Dessa forma, \(\frac{1}{k_{\text{evento}}}\) não representa a probabilidade implícita do evento estimada pela casa. Representa, no máximo, uma <em>proxy</em> dessa quantidade.</p> <p>Uma evidência adicional dessa afirmação é que a soma \(\frac{1}{k_{\text{Mandante}}} + \frac{1}{k_{\text{Visitante}}} + \frac{1}{k_{\text{Empate}}}\) é usualmente maior que \(1\). Por exemplo, consultando as cotações de uma famosa plataforma para o majestoso clássico entre Sydney Olympic vs Sydney United, temos as seguintes cotações: \(4.00\) (vitória Sydney Olympic), \(1.80\) (Sydney United) e \(3.60\) (empate). Ora, \(\frac{1}{4.00} + \frac{1}{1.80} + \frac{1}{3.60} = 108.3\)%. A soma das “probabilidades” é superior a \(100\)%.</p> <p>4) <strong>Por que a soma é superior a 1?</strong></p> <p>Este é o ingrediente que permite as casas garantirem lucros que independem do resultado final da partida. Sejam \(k_{i}\) as cotações de cada evento e \(V_{i}\) os respectivos valores apostados. O “lucro operacional” da plataforma será dado pelo que ela arrecada de apostas derrotadas menos o que ela precisa pagar aos vencedores.</p> <p>No caso da <strong>vitória do mandante</strong>, o <em>bottom line</em> operacional da plataforma é dado por:</p> \[V_{\text{Visitante}} + V_{\text{Empate}} - (k_{\text{Mandante}}-1)V_{\text{Mandante}}\] <p>Analogamente, em caso de <strong>vitória do visitante</strong>:</p> \[V_{\text{Mandante}} + V_{\text{Empate}} - (k_{\text{Visitante}}-1)V_{\text{Visitante}}\] <p>Finalmente, se a partida termina <strong>empatada</strong>:</p> \[V_{\text{Mandante}} + V_{\text{Visitante}} - (k_{\text{Empate}}-1)V_{\text{Empate}}\] <p>Para que a casa de apostas tenha lucro em qualquer caso, basta que as três expressões sejam positivas.</p> \[\begin{cases} V_{\text{Visitante}} + V_{\text{Empate}} - (k_{\text{Mandante}}-1)V_{\text{Mandante}} &gt; 0 \\ V_{\text{Mandante}} + V_{\text{Empate}} - (k_{\text{Visitante}}-1)V_{\text{Visitante}} &gt; 0 \\ V_{\text{Mandante}} + V_{\text{Visitante}} - (k_{\text{Empate}}-1)V_{\text{Empate}} &gt; 0 \end{cases} \implies \begin{cases} V_{\text{Mandante}} &lt; \frac{V_{\text{Visitante}} + V_{\text{Empate}}}{k_{\text{Mandante}}-1} \\ V_{\text{Visitante}} &lt; \frac{V_{\text{Mandante}} + V_{\text{Empate}}}{k_{\text{Visitante}}-1} \\ V_{\text{Empate}} &lt; \frac{V_{\text{Mandante}} + V_{\text{Visitante}}}{k_{\text{Empate}}-1} \end{cases}\] <p>Seja \(V\) o volume financeiro total de apostas para aquela partida, ou seja, \(V = V_{\text{Mandante}} + V_{\text{Visitante}} + V_{\text{Empate}}\). As inequações anteriores podem ser reescritas como (lembrando que \(k_{i} = \frac{1}{p_i}\)):</p> \[V_{i} &lt; \frac{V - V_{i}}{k_{i} - 1} \implies V_{i}k_{i} &lt; V \implies V_{i} &lt; \frac{V}{k_{i}} \implies V_{i} &lt; p_{i}V\] <p>Dessa forma, dado um conjunto de cotações, basta encontrarmos \(V_{\text{Mandante}}\), \(V_{\text{Visitante}}\) e \(V_{\text{Empate}}\) tais que:</p> \[\begin{cases} V_{i} &lt; p_{i}V \\ \sum_{i} V_i = V \end{cases}\] <p>O fato de que \(\sum_{i} p_i &gt; 1\) faz com que o sistema tenha solução para qualquer volume financeiro \(V\) (isto fica como exercício para o leitor). Portanto, seja qual for o resultado da partida, se a distribuição das apostas estiver coerente com as restrições acima, a casa ganhará dinheiro.</p> <p>Obviamente, o leitor atento certamente percebeu que estamos sendo pouco precisos com os termos contábeis desta seção. As casas incorrem múltiplos custos operacionais (custos de servidores, equipes de programadores, cientistas de dados, etc), e despesas (e.g. <em>marketing</em>) e, dessa forma, o que temos chamado de <em>lucro</em>, não o é de fato.</p> <p>Além disso, no raciocício acima, fixamos as cotações e assumimos que a casa é capaz de ajustar os volumes de cada aposta. Na realidade, este processo ocorre de maneira dinâmica, com a plataforma oferecendo cotações mais ou menos vantajosas ao longo do tempo para ajustar o portfólio de apostas.</p> <p>5) <strong>É possível bater o mercado (i.e. obter retornos positivos interesantes de maneira consistente)?</strong></p> <p>Se eu soubesse a resposta dessa pergunta, provavelmente estaria tomando um <em>mojito</em> em uma praia do Caribe e não escrevendo um post de um blog que (quase) ninguém lê. Em teoria, alguém que dispõe de um modelo preditivo de altíssima acurácia (em outras palavras, cujas estimativas das distribuições de probabilidade dos resultados seja, de fato, muito próximas das reais) poderia apostar em jogos em que haja discordância em relação às “probabilidades implícitas” nas cotações. Ou seja, se a casa precifica uma cotação cuja probabilidade implícita de vitória do mandante é de 30% e o seu poderoso modelo indica 90%, deve valer a pena comprar esta aposta. No longo prazo, esta estratégia deve quase certamente retornar lucros consistentes. No entanto, é evidente que obter um tal sistema preditivo é extremamente complicado. Lembre-se que as principais casas de apostas empregam vastas equipes de cientistas de dados trabalhando nos modelos de cotação e, portanto, “superá-los” não é uma tarefa simples.</p> <p>Existem, porém, alternativas que não dependem da criação de sistemas proprietários. <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.02824">Kaunitz, Zhong &amp; Kreiner (2017)</a> apresentam uma estratégia baseada na comparação de cotações providas por várias plataformas. O ponto mais interessante do artigo, entretanto, é o fato de que as casas começaram a dificultar as apostas dos pesquisadores assim que a estratégia se provou capaz de originar retornos positivos de maneira consistente. Isso mostra que as plataformas exercem uma discriminação operacional contra apostadores recorrentemente vitoriosos.</p> <p>Quem faz dinheiro com apostas esportivas são as casas, não os apostadores. Afinal, o patrocínio master do seu clube é provavelmente uma <em>bet</em> qualquer e não o nome do seu vizinho.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[sports betting in Brazil]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why can small countries form great national squads?</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/selecao-brasileira-dominio-distribuicao-maximo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why can small countries form great national squads?"/><published>2023-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/selecao-brasileira-dominio-distribuicao-maximo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/selecao-brasileira-dominio-distribuicao-maximo/"><![CDATA[<p>09/12/2022: Croatia eliminates Brazil in the quarterfinals of the World Cup. Besides the indignation of seeing Vinicius Junior, the most decisive player on the team, being substituted halfway through the second half, I wonder whether another issue torments the general public: <strong>how can Brazil, a country with a population of ~210 million people, lose (again) against such a small country (population-wise) like Croatia (~4 million)?</strong></p> <p>Indeed, Uruguay, Chile, Portugal, the Netherlands, Croatia, among several other small countries, are capable of producing successive generations that are technically comparable to those of more populous nations such as Brazil, Germany, and France.</p> <p>Naturally, this discussion demands a multidimensional analysis. Evidently, it is not enough to be large; it is necessary that the sport is practiced on a large scale and that there are mechanisms for talent scouting. Furthermore, there is a minimum level of essential infrastructure - especially coaches, fields, and youth championships - for the technical and tactical development of athletes. South America and Europe seem to offer such a developmental structure.</p> <p>Let us restrict ourselves to countries where football is an important cultural component. Let’s return to the central question of the article. The explanation I propose next is nothing more than a probabilistic argument based on some hypotheses that will be stated. More importantly, I do not believe there is a simple way to test the validity of these hypotheses. In other words, what I offer here is a way to think about the problem, rather than a definitive solution (a conclusion that the more skeptical reader would certainly already have in mind).</p> <p>Let’s move forward.</p> <p>A country is capable of forming \(n\) teams to play a football match, and the national team is defined as the best among them. Suppose we are able to define a quantity \(H\) that measures the technical level of a team (which we will vaguely call <em>skill</em>). The skill of the population (in the statistical sense) is distributed according to an unknown probability distribution (\(H \sim F_H\)), and the \(n\) teams that the country is capable of forming with its people constitute a random sample \(\lbrace H_1, ..., H_n \rbrace\) where each \(H_i\) is an independent copy of \(H\).</p> <p>Now, let’s state a restrictive hypothesis: suppose that this skill is confined to a finite interval \(H \in [0, c]\), that is, there is a maximum skill that no team can surpass - which will be represented by \(c\) in honor of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2003_Campeonato_Brasileiro_S%C3%A9rie_A">Cruzeiro (2003)</a>, which was probably the only team in the history of football to reach it. I propose we understand this maximum skill bound as derived from human physical constraints, after all, there are, a priori, limitations on how fast we can run or react, for example.</p> <p>With this description, the skill of the national team can be defined as the random variable \(H_S = \max \lbrace H_1, ..., H_n \rbrace\). The question now is: how is \(H_S\) distributed? For this, we will take a small number \(\epsilon\) and compute \(\mathbb{P}(H_S \geq c - \epsilon)\), which will allow us to get an idea of how the probability that the national team approaches the maximum skill behaves for sufficiently large \(n\).</p> <p>We have:</p> \[\begin{aligned} \mathbb{P}(H_S \geq c - \epsilon) &amp; = \mathbb{P}(\max \lbrace H_1, ..., H_n \rbrace \geq c - \epsilon) \\ &amp; = 1 - \mathbb{P}(\max \lbrace H_1, ..., H_n \rbrace &lt; c - \epsilon) &amp;&amp; \text{(by complementarity)} \\ &amp; = 1 - \mathbb{P}(H_1 &lt; c - \epsilon, ..., H_n &lt; c - \epsilon) &amp;&amp; \text{(max being smaller is equivalent to all being smaller)} \\ &amp; = 1 - \prod_{i=1}^{n} \mathbb{P}(H_i &lt; c - \epsilon) &amp;&amp; \text{(independence)} \\ &amp; = 1 - \prod_{i=1}^{n} F_H(c - \epsilon) &amp;&amp; \text{(identically distributed)} \\ &amp; = 1 - F_H(c - \epsilon)^n \\ \end{aligned}\] <p>Note that for any \(\epsilon &gt; 0\), even if very small, \(F_H(c - \epsilon) &lt; 1\), since the cumulative distribution function will only reach the value 1 at \(c\). In this case,</p> \[F_H(c - \epsilon) &lt; 1 \implies F_H(c - \epsilon)^n \xrightarrow[n \to \infty]{} 0\] <p>Therefore, for all \(\epsilon &gt; 0\),</p> \[\mathbb{P}(H_S \geq c - \epsilon) \xrightarrow[n \to \infty]{} 1\] <p>In other words, the probability that the national team exhibits a skill arbitrarily close to the maximum limit converges to 1 as the population size (or more precisely, the number of teams the country is capable of forming) increases. However, we do not have the speed of this convergence. I conjecture, though, that it is fast enough that an \(n\) on the order of hundreds of thousands or millions is sufficient for a quite reasonable approximation of \(c\) for most known distributions (we might possibly have to add some restrictions on the variances, but we will leave that aside for now).</p> <p>The interesting thing is that the phenomenon described above does not depend on the exact shape of the skill distribution for a country. It seems reasonable to assume that \(H_{\text{Brazil}}\) is a random variable with a higher mean than, say, Belgium \(H_{\text{Belgium}}\), and with a distribution more concentrated at higher skill levels. However, the national team is not dictated by the average skill, but by its maximum. And assuming this maximum skill bound exists, a football-active population with a few million inhabitants could be sufficient to find 11 extremely competitive players at the international level, as suggested by equation 2.</p> <p>Thus, it seems we will have to continue worrying about the national squads from small countries in Africa, South America, and Europe. Moreover, under the premise that football continues to develop in Asian countries and the United States, new powerful teams may emerge. In my view, Brazil should prepare to lose even more of its relative prominence in the international football scene but think about how to maintain its institutional power and image of <em>joga bonito</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a hypothetical (probabilistic) argument]]></summary></entry></feed>