<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-15T23:34:46+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Can Machines Think?</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/can-machines-think/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Machines Think?"/><published>2024-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/can-machines-think</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/can-machines-think/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an excerpt from a lecture given by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Feynman">Professor Richard Feynman</a> in 1985.</p> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ipRvjS7q1DI?si=gDqgSDOCXdgUKvxz" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[machine learning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Waiting Game - Why winning a World Cup takes time</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/winning-world-cup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Waiting Game - Why winning a World Cup takes time"/><published>2024-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/winning-world-cup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/winning-world-cup/"><![CDATA[<p>The last time Brazil lifted the World Cup trophy was over two decades ago. Since then, we have endured a series of painful eliminations, often at the hands of European teams - including the unforgettable 7-1 loss to Germany on home soil in 2014. This has been raising doubts about Brazil’s ability to obtain the much-dreamed-of sixth star.</p> <p>This article serves as a reminder of an important truth: winning a World Cup is incredibly difficult and it usually takes time. Although I believe that <a href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/blog/2023/selecao-brasileira-dominio-distribuicao-maximo/">Brazil’s relative prominence in the international football scene tends to diminish</a>, there is no need for over-pessimism concerning our capacity to win once more. Chances are that our time will come again.</p> <p><strong>How long is a reasonable wait for another title?</strong> Given that at least 5-6 teams usually have similar chances of winning each tournament (Brazil, Germany, Italy, Argentina, and France are perennial favorites, with teams like the Netherlands and Spain occasionally fielding strong squads), Brazil would statistically win the World Cup <strong>on average</strong> once every 5-6 editions, or every 20-24 years. For instance, Brazil took 24 years to win its fourth World Cup after 1970, just as Germany did after 1990 and Italy after 1982. Similarly, France waited 20 years after 1998, and Argentina endured a 36-year gap following their 1986 victory. Long waits are not an exception; they are the norm. And this makes sense from a statistical standpoint under our initial assumption.</p> <p><strong>The path to victory: a simple probabilistic perspective</strong>: Suppose Brazil always reaches the knockout stage, as it historically has. To win the World Cup, a team must win four consecutive playoff games (increasing to five under the new 48-team format). If Brazil enters each playoff match with a 60% chance of winning, the overall probability of becoming champions is just 13% (\(0.6^4\)). The breakdown of <em>elimination chances</em> at each stage is as follows: Round of 16 (40%), quarterfinals (24%), semifinals (14%), and final (9%)*. Under these conditions, Brazil is expected to be eliminated before the semifinals about 65% of the time. Even with a 70% match-winning probability, the odds of winning the tournament rise only to around 25%, and the team is still expected to exit before the semifinals half the time.</p> <p>Does this mean that Brazil’s fate is solely dictated by these probabilities and that nothing can be done to increase our chances? Absolutely not. Organization, tactical choices, and mental preparation may significantly improve match-winning probabilities, especially in early games like the Round of 16 and quarterfinals. In each of Brazil’s recent eliminations, one can identify (tactical) decisions that were clearly detrimental to the team’s performance during the game, potentially reducing the chances of progressing. However, we must recall that football is a stochastic game, and, at some point, dice will be played.</p> <p>A (possibly) funny note: In a recent interview after Brazil’s loss to Paraguay in the South American qualifiers, the Brazilian coach Dorival Junior boldly claimed that he guarantees he will be in <a href="https://www.espn.com.br/futebol/selecao-brasileira/artigo/_/id/14150159/dorival-junior-vai-conquistar-torcedor-crava-selecao-brasileira-final-copa-do-mundo-podem-me-cobrar">the World Cup final</a> in 2026. Given the odds outlined above, one might suggest that purchasing a ticket to the final could be his safest bet.</p> <p><em>*As an example, assuming independence between the results of each playoff match, the probability of elimination in the semifinals is given by: \(p_{\text{win}} \times p_{\text{win}} \times p_{\text{loss}} = 0.6 \times 0.6 \times 0.4 = 0.144\) (i.e. the probability of winning the round of 16 and winning the quarters and losing the semi).</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[football]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the gap in Brazil’s living standards</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/economics-living-standards-brazil/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the gap in Brazil’s living standards"/><published>2024-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/economics-living-standards-brazil</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/economics-living-standards-brazil/"><![CDATA[<p>This article is inspired by an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zs1lnsodeVA">interview given by the Brazilian economist Eduardo Moreira</a> to the public television network TV Brasil. It aims to provide a simple framework to understand why the economic model currently in place in Brazil cannot deliver on the promises of general social well-being in the next many decades.</p> <p>First, we notice that half of the Brazilian population (approximately 110 million people) live with an <a href="https://www.estadao.com.br/economia/1-mais-rico-325-vezes-metade-mais-pobre-ibge-nprei/">average monthly income per capita of R$540</a>. This means that the average household (roughly 3 people) receives around R$1.600 per month, or only ~20% above one minimum wage (as of 2024). As a reference: the <a href="https://exame.com/mercado-imobiliario/preco-medio-do-aluguel-no-pais-sobe-375-no-primeiro-trimestre-veja-valor-por-capital/">average rent</a> for a \(50m^2\) apartment in Sao Paulo (Brazil’s largest city) is R$2.650, and in Fortaleza (the cheapest capital for which data was available in the news) is R$1.450. It is absolutely clear that the bottom-50%’s monthly income is not enough to provide a decent basic living standard in urban areas.</p> <p>Defining a lower bound for an adequate monthly income is a difficult task, however, let’s consider for now <a href="https://valorinveste.globo.com/objetivo/gastar-bem/noticia/2023/08/04/salario-minimo-ideal-deveria-ser-de-r-r-652893-diz-dieese.ghtml">Dieese’s estimate of around R$1.650 per capita</a>. This implies that each person in the bottom-50% would have to increase their income by approximately R$1.100 in current terms (i.e. from R$540 to R$1.650).</p> <p>Hence we would need an aggregate additional income of R$1.100/person x 110 million people = R$121 billion per month. In a year, R$121 billion/month x 12 months = R$1.45 trillion. We have an issue though: according to the <a href="https://wid.world/country/brazil/">World Inequality Database</a>, Brazil’s bottom-50%’s share in the national income is historically around 10%, which means that in order to generate R$1.45 trillion for this part of the population, the whole economy would need an income injection of R$1.45 trillion/0.10 = R$14.5 trillion. <a href="https://www.ibge.gov.br/explica/pib.php">Brazil’s GDP</a> in 2023 was R$11 trillion. In order words, we would need to more than double the size of our economy* so that the bottom-50% would meet the <em>lower-bound</em> of the basic income.</p> <p>In the last 20 years, <a href="https://odsbrasil.gov.br/objetivo8/indicador811">Brazil’s GDP per capita has grown</a> approximately 1.3% per year in real terms. At this rate, obtaining the desired GDP would take 65 years. As people usually have children between 20-30 years of age, we are talking about 2-3 generations living below decent standards for half of our population. This is unacceptable.</p> <p>One should not miss the fact that our rough estimates are very sensitive to one particular piece of data: the small share (10%) of the national income that goes to the 50% poorest households. Suppose that this share was actually 20% (as <a href="https://wid.world/country/france/">in France</a>). Then, the needed additional annual income would be R$7.2 trillion (much lower than the previous R$14.5 trillion), which could be reached in 39 years (vs 65 before) under the same assumptions.</p> <p>This analysis reinforces the idea that economic growth alone will not be enough to alter the social reality of Brazil, and income redistribution mechanisms (e.g. tax system, social programs, etc) are equally important.</p> <p><em>*I am not a specialist in the definition of the GDP (far from it actually), but I wonder whether we should adjust to the fact that the <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/labor-share-of-gdp">labor share of the GDP</a> is historically close to 65%, or if this is somewhat already encoded in the figures above. If indeed this adjustment is fair, then the correct value for the additional needed income would be R$14.5 trillion/0.65 = R$22 trillion.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[economics and society]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A few words about the 48-team World Cup</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/world-cup-48-teams/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A few words about the 48-team World Cup"/><published>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/world-cup-48-teams</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/world-cup-48-teams/"><![CDATA[<p>From 2026 on, the Men’s Football World Cup will be played by 48 national teams, instead of the usual 32. The teams will be <a href="https://inside.fifa.com/about-fifa/organisation/fifa-council/media-releases/fifa-council-approves-international-match-calendars">divided into 12 groups of 4</a>, playing a single round-robin tournament, from which the top two and eight best third-placed will be qualified for the playoffs.</p> <p>It is not unreasonable to assume that FIFA’s main motivations behind the inclusion of 16 new countries are money (higher TV &amp; advertisement, and game-day revenues) and power (more political support from the confederations benefitted by the expansion), and those arguments <a href="https://www.uol.com.br/esporte/futebol/colunas/juca-kfouri/2023/10/04/a-copa-do-mundo-em-seis-paises.htm">find echo on a relevant part of the sports media</a>.</p> <p>Although I understand and agree with this view, I must confess that I think that the consequences of the expansion will be fantastic. First, <a href="https://www.bbc.com/sport/football/39448474">Africa is receiving 4 new spots</a>, while Asia is getting 3. Given the low representation of those continents in past editions of the competition, and also considering their recent strong performances, those places are definitely well-deserved. Additionally, Europe is taking 3 new places, which decreases the chances that football powerhouses such as Italy or the Netherlands will stay out of the tournament as happened before. Finally, South America and its highly competitive qualifiers receive one extra spot. This means that we are guaranteed to have several additional nations for which football is a central cultural aspect playing in the World Cup.</p> <p>Many journalists have <a href="https://blogdojuliogomes.blogosfera.uol.com.br/2017/01/11/duas-razoes-para-nao-gostar-da-copa-do-mundo-com-48-selecoes/">pointed out that the extra teams could decrease the technical level of the competition or even diminish the competitiveness of the regional qualifiers</a>. This may be true. However, do we really care about the technical level in a World Cup? Do we care about the qualifiers in general? I would safely assume that both answers are negative for most football supporters. For the first question, I would argue that the appeal of a World Cup is primarily driven by emotion rather than skill, especially at a time when European club football already provides weekly exhibitions of refined technique. As for the second question, it’s worth noting that the qualifiers already face a general lack of interest (at least in Brazil), except for a few notable matches (e.g. against Argentina).</p> <p>Enough of my personal opinion. Let’s take one step back, and discuss the format of a World Cup with 48 teams. Before settling for the 12 groups with 4 teams scenario, FIFA had initially proposed 16 groups with 3 teams, with the top two classifying for playoffs. At that time, <a href="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f1af76ed86d6771ad48324b/606e51a178c5517440a676f1_JulienGuyon-FIFACollusion-RPpaper.pdf">this article written by the French mathematician Julien Guyon</a> gained prominence. In this paper, Guyon discusses the risk of collusion (i.e. the teams playing the last game of the group potentially match fixing so both advance) in groups of 3 teams and shows that the probability of collusion in at least one group is very high. The author also suggests alternative formats that could reduce the risk of collusion, and, interestingly, FIFA has adopted one of them. I am not aware of the impact of this particular paper (or the related literature) on the organization’s final decision, but it is always interesting to see how scientific reasoning can sometimes help us to make robustly improved decisions.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[football world cup]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How do Brazilian engineering schools’ budgets compare globally?</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/engineering-budget/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How do Brazilian engineering schools’ budgets compare globally?"/><published>2024-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/engineering-budget</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2024/engineering-budget/"><![CDATA[<p>Some weeks ago, I attended the <a href="https://www.tudelft.nl/en/2024/me/news/tu-delft-mechanical-engineering-opens-new-robotics-lab">opening of one of TU Delft’s robotics labs</a> and was impressed by its infrastructure. This experience prompted me to consider whether such an investment would be feasible for a Brazilian engineering school. Not having the time for a proper analysis, I choose to present some relevant data that I quickly gathered comparing the budgets of one of Brazil’s leading engineering schools with those of some of its international peers.</p> <p>According to the University of São Paulo’s <a href="https://sites.usp.br/codage/gestao-orcamentaria/prestacao-de-contas/">budget plan</a>, the Polytechnic School (its engineering unit) is expected to have approximately R$ 375 million (or EUR 67 million) to spend in 2024. With around <a href="https://www.poli.usp.br/institucional/poli-em-numeros">8,500 FTE (Full-Time Employees)</a> (including undergraduate and graduate students, faculty, and administrative staff), the annual budget per FTE comes to about EUR 7,900.</p> <p>In contrast, TU Delft (Netherlands) had <a href="https://filelist.tudelft.nl/TUDelft/Over_TU_Delft/Feiten_Cijfers/jaarverslagen/TU%20Delft%20Jaarverslag%202022%20EN%20%28def%29.pdf">funding of around EUR 880 million</a> for 30,000 FTE in 2022, resulting in a ratio of EUR 29,000 per FTE, more than three times higher than the Brazilian school. At École Polytechnique (France), <a href="https://www.ccomptes.fr/system/files/2020-02/20200225-12-TomeI-ecole-polytechnique.pdf">a public report</a> indicates that the annual formation cost per student was about EUR 36,000 in 2016-17 (though this figure is not directly comparable to the other schools, it provides a rough estimate). Lastly, Polytechnique Montreal (Canada) <a href="https://www.polymtl.ca/renseignements-generaux/en/about-polytechnique">operates with a budget of EUR 150 million</a> for 10,000 FTE (2018-19), leading to EUR 15,000 per FTE, or twice the ratio of the Brazilian school.</p> <p>I point the interested reader to these schools’ annual reports to understand the specific details (sources, destinations, distribution of FTE, profile of the research programs, etc) of each budget. Needless to say, any errors in the data presented above are my responsibility, and these figures represent my best interpretation of the annual reports.</p> <p>Despite the limited depth of this analysis, the significant difference in budget per capita (2-3x) when comparing one of Brazil’s leading engineering schools with other top-tier international schools suggests that Brazilian engineering may lack the resources needed to compete globally.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[engineering]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The big casino of sports betting</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/sports-betting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The big casino of sports betting"/><published>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/sports-betting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/sports-betting/"><![CDATA[<p>The sports betting houses have <a href="https://www.uol.com.br/esporte/futebol/ultimas-noticias/2023/03/31/patrocinios-de-sites-de-apostas-a-clubes-da-serie-a-batem-r-330-mi-por-ano.htm">taken over Brazilian football</a> in recent years. Their brands seem ubiquitous: advertising on TV and the internet, sponsorships on uniforms, and billboards. Interestingly, until very recently, these companies benefited from regulatory and tax loopholes that provided additional incentives for the proliferation of their activity - a situation that should be (at least partially) addressed with an <a href="https://g1.globo.com/politica/noticia/2023/07/25/mp-das-apostas.ghtml">executive order by Minister Haddad</a>.</p> <p>But what is behind the interest of so many agents in mediating sports bets? What are the fundamentals of the profitability of this activity? In this article, I intend to present some reflections on the mathematics and economics of sports betting. Although I am using the term <em>sports</em>, I should add that I will focus on football betting. Additionally, I will discuss the “standard” bets (i.e. betting on who won the match) - which I assume to account for most of the money spent on those platforms.</p> <p>1) <strong>Explaining the odds</strong></p> <p>For the standard bets, for each game, the house sets odds for a home team win, an away team win, and a draw. For example, let’s imagine that Real Madrid will face Barcelona, and a betting platform has set the following odds for each result: 2.5 if Real Madrid wins, 3.0 if Barcelona wins, and 1.5 if the match ends in a draw. If one bets R$1 in a Real Madrid victory, one receives R$2.5 if this event indeed happens (yielding a return of R$1.5, as the initial R$1 is part of the payout), and alternatively loses the initial R$1 if any other result takes place. In other words, the bottom line for this bettor is either a profit of R$1.5 if Real Madrid wins, or a loss of R$1 else. Analogously, betting on Barcelona yields a return of +R$2.0 (Barcelona wins) or -R$1 (else), and on a draw leads to +R$0.5 in the case of score equality, or again -R$1 if any other result.</p> <p>2) <strong>Why can \(\frac{1}{\text{odds}}\) represent the probability of the event?</strong></p> <p>In our previous example, many sites will indicate that the probability of a draw implied by the odds of 1.5 is \(\frac{1}{1.5} \approx 67\%\). But how is this calculation justified?</p> <p>My current understanding is that this comes from a <em>perfect competition</em> argument. In a perfectly competitive market among betting houses, the odds should be set such that the expected return for the bettor is zero (if the odds implied positive expected returns, the house would lose money in the long run; if negative, other houses could offer better odds and capture market share).</p> <p>Let \(R\) be the random variable representing the return of the bettor for each R$1 bet, and \(k_{\text{event}}\) be the odds for a particular event (e.g., home team victory).</p> \[R = \begin{cases} k_{\text{event}}-1 &amp; \text{if the event occurs } (\text{w/ probability } p_{\text{event}}) \\ -1 &amp; \text{if not } (\text{w/ probability } 1-p_{\text{event}}) \end{cases}\] <p>Therefore,</p> \[\mathbb{E}(R) = (k_{\text{event}}-1)p_{\text{event}} + (-1)(1-p_{\text{event}}) = 0 \implies p_{\text{event}} = \frac{1}{k_{\text{event}}}\] <p>In other words, if the house believes that the probability of the event is 50%, then, under perfect competition, it would be “forced” (by market dynamics) to offer odds of \(k_{\text{event}} = \frac{1}{p_{\text{event}}} = \frac{1}{0.5} = 2\). This is a simplified explanation, but it helps to understand the rationale. Similar arguments (and with greater formalization) can be found in basic Microeconomics textbooks.</p> <p>3) <strong>Is the perfect competition hypothesis valid in practice?</strong></p> <p>No. There is no perfect competition in this market (which resembles more of an oligopoly), and there are operational costs that the house must cover.</p> <p>Thus, \(\frac{1}{k_{\text{event}}}\) does not represent the house’s estimated implicit probability of the event. At most, it is a <em>proxy</em> for this quantity.</p> <p>An additional piece of evidence for this claim is that the sum \(\frac{1}{k_{\text{Home}}} + \frac{1}{k_{\text{Away}}} + \frac{1}{k_{\text{Draw}}}\) is usually greater than 1. For example, looking at the odds from a popular platform for the grand match between Sydney Olympic vs. Sydney United, we have the following odds: 4.00 (Sydney Olympic win), 1.80 (Sydney United win), and 3.60 (draw). Note that \(\frac{1}{4.00} + \frac{1}{1.80} + \frac{1}{3.60} = 108.3\)%. The sum of the “probabilities” exceeds 100%.</p> <p>4) <strong>Why does the sum exceed 1?</strong></p> <p>This is the mechanism that allows houses to ensure profits regardless of the final match result. Let \(k_{i}\) be the odds for each event, and \(V_{i}\) the respective amounts bet. The platform’s “operational profit” will be the amount collected from losing bets minus the amount paid to the winners.</p> <p>In the case of a <strong>home win</strong>, the platform’s operational bottom line is given by:</p> \[V_{\text{Away}} + V_{\text{Draw}} - (k_{\text{Home}}-1)V_{\text{Home}}\] <p>Similarly, in the case of an <strong>away win</strong>:</p> \[V_{\text{Home}} + V_{\text{Draw}} - (k_{\text{Away}}-1)V_{\text{Away}}\] <p>Finally, if the match ends in a <strong>draw</strong>:</p> \[V_{\text{Home}} + V_{\text{Away}} - (k_{\text{Draw}}-1)V_{\text{Draw}}\] <p>For the betting house to profit in any scenario, all three expressions must be positive. Assuming \(k_i &gt; 1\) (which is always the case, as otherwise the bettor is guaranteed to lose money):</p> \[\begin{cases} V_{\text{Away}} + V_{\text{Draw}} - (k_{\text{Home}}-1)V_{\text{Home}} &gt; 0 \\ V_{\text{Home}} + V_{\text{Draw}} - (k_{\text{Away}}-1)V_{\text{Away}} &gt; 0 \\ V_{\text{Home}} + V_{\text{Away}} - (k_{\text{Draw}}-1)V_{\text{Draw}} &gt; 0 \end{cases} \iff \begin{cases} V_{\text{Home}} &lt; \frac{V_{\text{Away}} + V_{\text{Draw}}}{k_{\text{Home}}-1} \\ V_{\text{Away}} &lt; \frac{V_{\text{Home}} + V_{\text{Draw}}}{k_{\text{Away}}-1} \\ V_{\text{Draw}} &lt; \frac{V_{\text{Home}} + V_{\text{Away}}}{k_{\text{Draw}}-1} \end{cases}\] <p>Let \(V\) be the total financial volume of bets for that match, i.e., \(V = V_{\text{Home}} + V_{\text{Away}} + V_{\text{Draw}}\). The previous inequalities can be rewritten as (remembering that \(k_{i} = \frac{1}{p_i}\)):</p> \[V_{i} &lt; \frac{V - V_{i}}{k_{i} - 1} \iff V_{i}k_{i} &lt; V \iff V_{i} &lt; \frac{V}{k_{i}} \iff V_{i} &lt; p_{i}V\] <p>Thus, given a set of odds, we need to find \(V_{\text{Home}}\), \(V_{\text{Away}}\) e \(V_{\text{Draw}}\) such that:</p> \[\begin{cases} V_{i} &lt; p_{i}V \\ \sum_{i} V_i = V \end{cases}\] <p>The fact that \(\sum_{i} p_i &gt; 1\) ensures that the system has a solution for any financial volume \(V\) (this is left as an exercise for the reader). Therefore, regardless of the match outcome, if the distribution of bets respects the above constraints, the house will make money.</p> <p>Of course, attentive readers will notice that we are being somewhat imprecise with the accounting terms in this section. Houses incur multiple operational costs (server costs, teams of programmers, data scientists, etc.) and expenses (e.g., marketing), so what we have been calling profit is not quite that.</p> <p>Moreover, in the reasoning above, we fixed the odds and assumed the house could adjust the volume of each bet. In reality, this process occurs dynamically, with the platform offering more or less advantageous odds over time to balance the bet distribution.</p> <p>5) <strong>Is it possible to beat the market (i.e., consistently achieve positive returns)?</strong></p> <p>This is highly unlikely. Outperforming the platforms’ predictive models is extremely hard and, even in the unlikely scenario where you find a way, betting houses seem to be able to hinder some strategies as soon as they are proven capable of consistently generating positive returns (as showed in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.02824">this paper</a>).</p> <p>Your football club is sponsored by a betting company, not by your neighbor. So my recommendation is to always remember who is really making the money in this activity before falling into the illusion of getting rich quickly.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[sports betting in Brazil]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why can small countries form great national squads?</title><link href="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/selecao-brasileira-dominio-distribuicao-maximo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why can small countries form great national squads?"/><published>2023-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/selecao-brasileira-dominio-distribuicao-maximo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eduardofmdcosta.github.io/al-folio/blog/2023/selecao-brasileira-dominio-distribuicao-maximo/"><![CDATA[<p>09/12/2022: Croatia eliminates Brazil in the quarterfinals of the World Cup. Besides the indignation of seeing Vinicius Junior, the most decisive player on the team, being substituted halfway through the second half, I wonder whether another issue torments the general public: <strong>How can Brazil, a country with a population of ~210 million people, lose (again) against such a small country (population-wise) like Croatia (~4 million)?</strong></p> <p>Indeed, Uruguay, Chile, Portugal, the Netherlands, and Croatia, among several other small countries, are capable of producing successive generations that are technically comparable to those of more populous nations such as Brazil, Germany, and France.</p> <p>Naturally, this discussion demands a multidimensional analysis. It is not enough to be large; it is necessary that the sport is practiced on a large scale and that there are mechanisms for talent scouting. Furthermore, there is a minimum level of essential infrastructure - especially coaches, fields, and youth championships - for the technical and tactical development of athletes. South America and Europe seem to offer such a developmental structure.</p> <p>Let us restrict ourselves to countries where football is an important cultural component. Let’s return to the central question of the article. The explanation I propose next is nothing more than a probabilistic argument based on some hypotheses that will be stated. More importantly, I do not believe there is a simple way to test the validity of these hypotheses. In other words, what I offer here is a way to think about the problem, rather than a definitive solution (a conclusion that the more skeptical reader would certainly already have in mind).</p> <p>Let’s move forward.</p> <p>A country is capable of forming \(n\) teams to play a football match, and the national team is defined as the best among them. Suppose we are able to define a quantity \(H\) that measures the technical level of a team (which we will vaguely call <em>skill</em>). The skill of the population (in the statistical sense) is distributed according to an unknown probability distribution (\(H \sim F_H\)), and the \(n\) teams that the country is capable of forming with its people constitute a random sample \(\lbrace H_1, ..., H_n \rbrace\) where each \(H_i\) is an independent copy of \(H\).</p> <p>Now, let’s state a restrictive hypothesis: suppose that this skill is confined to a finite interval \(H \in [0, c]\), that is, there is a maximum skill that no team can surpass - which will be represented by \(c\) in honor of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2003_Campeonato_Brasileiro_S%C3%A9rie_A">Cruzeiro (2003)</a>, which was probably the only team in the history of football to reach it. I propose we understand this maximum skill bound as derived from human physical constraints, after all, there are, a priori, limitations on how fast we can run or react, for example.</p> <p>With this description, the skill of the national team can be defined as the random variable \(H_S = \max \lbrace H_1, ..., H_n \rbrace\). The question now is: how is \(H_S\) distributed? For this, we will take a small number \(\epsilon\) and compute \(\mathbb{P}(H_S \geq c - \epsilon)\), which will allow us to get an idea of how the probability that the national team approaches the maximum skill behaves for sufficiently large \(n\).</p> <p>We have:</p> \[\begin{aligned} \mathbb{P}(H_S \geq c - \epsilon) &amp; = \mathbb{P}(\max \lbrace H_1, ..., H_n \rbrace \geq c - \epsilon) \\ &amp; = 1 - \mathbb{P}(\max \lbrace H_1, ..., H_n \rbrace &lt; c - \epsilon) &amp;&amp; \text{(by complementarity)} \\ &amp; = 1 - \mathbb{P}(H_1 &lt; c - \epsilon, ..., H_n &lt; c - \epsilon) &amp;&amp; \text{(max being smaller is equivalent to all being smaller)} \\ &amp; = 1 - \prod_{i=1}^{n} \mathbb{P}(H_i &lt; c - \epsilon) &amp;&amp; \text{(independence)} \\ &amp; = 1 - \prod_{i=1}^{n} F_H(c - \epsilon) &amp;&amp; \text{(identically distributed)} \\ &amp; = 1 - F_H(c - \epsilon)^n \\ \end{aligned}\] <p>Note that for any \(\epsilon &gt; 0\), even if very small, \(F_H(c - \epsilon) &lt; 1\), since the cumulative distribution function will only reach the value 1 at \(c\). In this case,</p> \[F_H(c - \epsilon) &lt; 1 \implies F_H(c - \epsilon)^n \xrightarrow[n \to \infty]{} 0\] <p>Therefore, for all \(\epsilon &gt; 0\),</p> \[\mathbb{P}(H_S \geq c - \epsilon) \xrightarrow[n \to \infty]{} 1\] <p>In other words, the probability that the national team exhibits a skill arbitrarily close to the maximum limit converges to 1 as the population size (or more precisely, the number of teams the country is capable of forming) increases. However, we do not have the speed of this convergence. I conjecture, though, that it is fast enough that an \(n\) on the order of hundreds of thousands or millions is sufficient for a quite reasonable approximation of \(c\) for most known distributions (we might possibly have to add some restrictions on the variances, but we will leave that aside for now).</p> <p>The interesting thing is that the phenomenon described above does not depend on the exact shape of the skill distribution for a country. It seems reasonable to assume that \(H_{\text{Brazil}}\) is a random variable with a higher mean than, say, Belgium \(H_{\text{Belgium}}\), and with a distribution more concentrated at higher skill levels. However, the national team is not dictated by the average skill, but by its maximum. Assuming this maximum skill bound exists, a football-active population with a few million inhabitants could be sufficient to find 11 extremely competitive players at the international level, as suggested by equation 2.</p> <p>Thus, it seems we will have to continue worrying about the national squads from small countries in Africa, South America, and Europe. Moreover, under the premise that football continues to develop in Asian countries and the United States, new powerful teams may emerge. In my view, Brazil should prepare to lose even more of its relative prominence in the international football scene but think about how to maintain its institutional power and image of <em>joga bonito</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a hypothetical (probabilistic) argument]]></summary></entry></feed>